Brooks A. Bentz Railroad Collection
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Brooks A. Bentz Railroad Collection.
undated, 1889, 1913-1975
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Bentz, Brooks A.
.75 linear foot.
The Brooks A. Bentz Railroad Collection consists almost exclusively of materials associated with the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, including passenger and employee timetables, a parlor car wine list and dining car cafe menu, information about the railroad equipment provided for railroad employees, information about the railroad's merger with what became Penn Central in the late 1960s, a vehicle decal, a map of the railroad system (ca. 1925), and photographs of locomotives.
MSS20030113
History
Brooks A. Bentz is a resident of Stonington, Connecticut. Beginning in 1969 he worked for various railroad companies, including Penn Central, Norfolk & Western Railway, Delaware & Hudson, and Boston & Maine Corporation in such capacities as brakeman, assistant trainmaster, agent/operator, marketing director, and General Manager of Intermodal Operations. In the late 1980s he was President and CEO of Ameritrans Corporation, AVP - Intermodal of Burlington Northern Railroad, and CEO of Trans-Star Trucking Company. Since 1991 he has worked as a transportation consultant.
Mr. Bentz is also a collector of historical railroad documents and memorabilia, including those of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad (a.k.a. New Haven Railroad).
Scope and Content
The Brooks A. Bentz Railroad Collection consists almost exclusively of materials associated with the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, including passenger and employee timetables, a parlor car wine list and dining car cafe menu, information about the railroad equipment provided for railroad employees, information about the railroad's merger with what became Penn Central in the late 1960s, a vehicle decal, a map of the railroad system (ca. 1925), and photographs of locomotives.
Arrangement
Series I: Papers, undated, 1889, 1913-1975. This series consists of a commemorative booklet about the effect that the New England Hurricane of 1938 had on the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, information about the brake equipment on cars and locomotives, reports of the company's trustees during the 1960s, passenger and employee timetables, a parlor car wine list and a dining car cafe menu, histories of the company written by its Public Relations Department, and testimony of Richard Joyce Smith, a trustee of the company, concerning the merger of Pennsylvania Railroad and the New York Central Railroad (which became known as Penn Central).
Series II: Ephemera, undated This series consists of R.P.O. cancellations of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad's Boston and New York train, and a company vehicle decal.
Series III: Map, 1925. The series contains a map of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad system.
Series IV: Photographs, 1931-1961. This series consists of nine builder's photographs of New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad diesel locomotives 0400, 0500, 0568, 0900, 0923, 0931, and 0973. It also includes one photograph of locomotive 2001 with a long line of passenger and freight cars.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial number of collections with information about southern New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Bentz, Brooks A.; Smith, Richard Joyce.
Organizations:
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company.; Penn Central Transportation Company.
Subjects:
Railroads--Connecticut.
Document Types:
Publications.; Photographs.; Maps.; Administrative Records.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Custodial History
The materials were collected and held by Mr. Bentz prior to their donation to Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries.
Acquisition Information
The records were donated by Mr. Brooks A. Bentz in 2003.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Papers, undated, 1889, 1913-1975
  - "The Devastation and Restoration of New England's Vital Life-Line," (commemorative booklet about the New England Hurricane of 1938), 1938 (Box 1:1)
  - Rules for the Government of the Operating Department for the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1954 (Box 1:2)
  - Air Brake Equipment on Cars, 1963 (Box 1:3)
  - Air Brake Equipment on Locomotives, 1963 (Box 1:4)
  - Track Safety Record, Federal Railroad Administration, U.S. Department of Transportation, 1975 (Box 1:5)
  - Reports of the Trustees on the Operations of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company, 1965-1968 (Box 1:6)
  - Passenger timetables, 1889, 1929, 1964, 1967, 1968 (Box 1:7)
  - Passenger timetables, lines west of New London and Willimantic, 1913 (Box 1:8)
  - Passenger timetables, Old Greenwich, Riverside, Cos Cob and Grand Central Terminal, 1939, 1943, 1948 (Box 1:9)
  - Passenger timetable, New York and Danbury, Pittsfield, Waterbury, 1968 (Box 1:10)
  - Passenger timetable, Cape Cod and Islands (reprint), undated (Box 1:11)
  - Passenger timetable, Penn Central New Haven region, 1969 (Box 1:12)
  - Passenger timetable, Boston & Maine Railroad, 1939, 1943, 1948 (Box 1:13)
  - Employee timetables, 1948, 1964, 1965, 1966 (Box 1:14)
  - Parlor Car wine list, 1968 (Box 1:15)
  - Dining Car cafe menu, 1968 (Box 1:16)
  - Summary of equipment, 1964-1968 (Box 2:17)
  - Special train symbol numbers, ca. 1968 (Box 2:18)
  - New Haven Division Pool Code List, ca. 1968 (Box 2:19)
  - Description and assignment [of] Air-Conditioned Passenger Cars, ca. 1968 (Box 2:20)
  - Histories of the New Haven Railroad (written by the Public Relations Dept.), undated (Box 2:21)
  - Information for news media about the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company, 1967 (Box 2:22)
  - Testimony of Richard Joyce Smith, Trustee of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company, concerning the merger with Pennsylvania Railroad and New York Central Railroad, [1967] (Box 2:23)
  - Track charts, [1967] (Box 2:24)
- Series II: Ephemera, undated, 1968
  - R.P.O. cancellations -- Boston and New York train, April 10 and April 11, 1968, 1968 (Box 2:25)
  - New Haven Railroad vehicle decal, undated (Box 2:26)
- Series III: Map, 1925
  - Map of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad system, ca. 1925 (Box 2:27)
- Series IV: Photographs, 1931-1961
  - Photographs (Box 2:28)
    - 2003-0113.ph1, diesel locomotive 0400, builder's photograph, 1947
    - 2003-0113.ph2, diesel locomotive 0450, builder's photograph, 1947
    - 2003-0113.ph3, diesel locomotive 0500 (switcher), builder's photograph, 1947
    - 2003-0113.ph4, diesel locomotive 0568 (switcher), builder's photograph, [1950]
    - 2003-0113.ph5, diesel locomotive 0900 (switcher), builder's photograph, 1931
    - 2003-0113.ph6, diesel locomotive 0931 (switcher), builder's photograph, 1938
    - 2003-0113.ph7, diesel locomotive 0923 (switcher), builder's photograph, 1940
    - 2003-0113.ph8, diesel locomotive 0931 (switcher), builder's photograph, 1941
    - 2003-0113.ph9, diesel locomotive 0973 (switcher), builder's photograph, 1947
    - 2003-0113.ph10, Locomotive 2001 with long line of passenger and freight cars, [1961?]